[Music]
Welcome to Business Central launch event
2025 release day one. In this session,
we will show you new functionality
related to sustainability, water and
waste
management. Okay, let's remind you what
was our primary focus in first two
waves. It was related to emissions and
specifically to these three different
emissions carbon, metan oxide. And we
added in previous wave carbo equivalent
as a new model for expression different
uh calculations. But now with this wave
we extend the functionality to water and
waste management. We did it before
because it was required by CSRD and some
other rules. So we want to cover all
requirements related to uh environmental
reporting. So from this way you can use
water and waste management as well.
Okay, let's see what we have there.
First, when you set up your account,
your new uh account for water, you can
go to sustainability category and choose
what you want to track, water intensity
or discharge into water. So, you can set
up for one category both of them or only
one or another. Now based on what you
set it up on uh your category you need
to make some you need you can make
additional configuration your
subcategory to use different formulas.
So if you're using water intensity in
category you can set up water intensity
factor. This is similar as you had
emission factors for different gas
emissions. And if you want to track
discharge into water you can set up
discharge into water factor. So you can
use custom formulas with these two
different
factors. Okay. What else we have related
to water? Related with water, we have
new option related to responsibility
centers. So we extend a little bit
responsibility centers as we can treat
responsibility centers as
facility. This is not mandatory. So you
can post uh all uh records related to
water without setting up uh
responsibility center. But in some
requirements you need to report u what
you discharge what your water intensity
was uh related and comparing with your
total capacity in your facility. So if
you want to report this way you need to
set up responsibility center. What you
can do there you can find the
sustainability fast tab water capacity
dimension and this is free textual uh
field. You can enter volume area depends
what is uh your capacity dimension you
want to use and then based on this you
need to configure capacity unit and
capacity quantity. In capacity unit you
need to use standard unit of measure and
then in uh capacity quantity you need to
put what is your total capacity related
to this facility or in our case
responsibility center business center.
Okay. Now let's switch to waste
management. In a v scope you can use
again category and in you need to choose
water way scope because this is common
scope. You have three different uh scope
one, scope two, scope three, autoscope
emissions and plus now we have water and
waste scope. You need to choose this one
and then you can uh enable waste
intensity. If you enable waste intensity
your category in subcategory you can
enter your waste intensity factor. If
you want to track if you have factors
and choose custom formula. So if you do
not have factors both for waste and
water you can enter your total uh
intensity in your journal and that's
absolutely okay. But this is additional
option. So you can use embedded formula
in the journal. Now let's see some
additional things related to uh water
and waste uh features when you want to
post into journal. So you will enter
your uh amounts but you need to choose
your waterbased intensity type. So if
you are posting water you can choose
withdrawn, discharge, consume, recycled
and if you want to uh post waste you can
choose between generated, disposed,
recovered. So you need you must choose
one of these integrity types. So we will
have record related to some of these
types in your sustainability ledger
entry. Then further if you are choosing
water except this water intensity type
you need to choose water type and you
can choose between surface water, sea
water, groundwater, third party water,
produce water. What do I want to uh to
emphasize both of these uh options are
enums so you can extend if you have
additional option to track okay let's
look how it look like in a
practice first I will open chart of
sustainability account so business as
usual you already use chart of
sustainability account for your
emissions now you have just new accounts
for water and for waste as you can see
on my screen now if you want to set up
first as I already mentioned we will
move to category and I will open water
category for example and then you will
see what you can or need to set up
because this is not mandatory actually
what is mandatory you need to choose uh
as a emission scope water and waste and
then you will choose if you want to
track water intensity or discharge into
water and you can choose custom formula
on my screen I didn't choose formal so
this is what I want to show you if you
do not want to use formulas, you can
leave this empty. If you want to use
formulas, you need to choose custom
formula. Only custom formula is related
to both water and waste management. And
you can add custom value uh actually
unit of measure you want to track with
your uh water and waste formulas. Then
that's it. Uh related to categories, you
just need to set up what you want to
track what you will enforce users to
enter into journal line. And then we can
look into
subcategory. And now when we open
subcategory again as I said you can
enter because what you can enter water
and waste intensity factor and discharge
into water factor. So again this is an
option this is not must. So if you have
factors you can enter this factor and
then you can use formulas. So if you
didn't have any factor you can easily go
into uh total uh total values and enter
your total values you know you want to
post. So again this is an optional. Okay
let's close and um let's switch to our
journals. When you prepare your journal
I have one example of different uh
options related to water and based in
this journal. What do you need to have?
You need to have values before posting
in
water minimum. Yeah, not in all of them.
I I made this combination. So depends if
you are uh based on your category what
you decided you want to track. So if you
want to track only water intensity, you
must have value in water intensity. If
you decided to post discharge into
water, you must have value there. And
the same if you decided to track waste,
you need to have value into waste
intensity. So you need to have these
values and then what is done with the
water and waste you need to choose I
already mentioned water and waste
intensity type again this is annual
field so you can choose what you want to
track there and if this is water related
you need to add additional water type
ground surface sea water and other types
of water and that's it this is what you
need to enter is a sustainability
journal after that you just need to post
this journal and that's it all these
values will finish in your
sustainability ledger entry the same way
as you are doing with your emissions.
What is difference with emissions? You
can track emissions with sustainability
journal with general journal from this
wave and purchase document but water and
waste intensity you can track only
through sustainability journal in this
moment what I wanted to show you
additional because you will have
probably some forecast related to water
and waste. So if you have sustainability
goals, if you're using sustainability
goals, now we added sustainability
goals, water and waste um intensity as a
targets as as a baseline. So you can
track against baseline and you can track
against um uh targets. Targets are free
values. So this is just your forecast.
Baseline is uh based on your previous
period you want to track. So everything
is absolutely the same as we had uh for
emissions in uh scorecards and goals
only two additional options
there. So thank you for watching this
session and I will invite you to watch
another sustainability related sessions
because for this wave we have eight
different session related to
sustainability. Thank you.